James Maciukenas, Ph.D.

💌 773-290-9947 🗳 blueform@gmail.com 🖪 Evanston, IL 🛅 http://www.linkedin.com/in/james-maciukenas

Profile

I am a highly skilled qualitative UX researcher with experience in mixed methods. I worked with some of the biggest names in the tech industry and delivered insights that guided product decisions and future research. My expertise lies in foundational and directional research exploring generative AI, search, digital assistants, and internal ad sales tools. My background in web design and development gives me a well-rounded understanding of the technical feasibility considerations that inform UX research recommendations.

The projects I worked on for a major tech industry client involved conducting iterative preand post-launch UX studies for a generative AI chatbot, as well as exploring how generative AI could be integrated into both new and legacy tools. It has been an exciting journey to be involved in exploring how generative AI impacts the way people approach computing, while also informing design and engineering teams of actionable research-driven insights.

While working with the UX agency AnswerLab, I conducted over 50 studies in 2 years, honing my research, collaboration, and communication skills while embedded with teams in a fast-paced environment. My background in design, communication, web development, analysis, and teaching also prepared me to tackle complex challenges through research, data gathering, evaluation, and sharing compelling narratives while reporting.

Experience

UX RESEARCHER, ANSWERLAB, REMOTE & CHICAGO, IL — MAR 2022-MAR 2024

- Delivered foundational and directional research for desktop and mobile.
- Skilled in developing and executing rapid and embedded research.
- Delivered actionable insights in compelling readouts fostering discussion for design and engineering teams.
- Findings led to product decisions and informed future research.

WEB DEVELOPER, INDIANA UNIVERSITY-BLOOMINGTON, IN — AUG 2019-MAR 2022

- Developed responsive UX standards-based web applications.
- Maintained and enforced ADA accessibility requirements for web applications.

WEB DEVELOPER & DESIGNER, ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (IIT), CHICAGO, IL — AUG 2005-2019

• Communicate student and faculty efforts through websites, newsletters, articles, and event marketing.

INSTRUCTOR, PUBLIC ENGAGEMENT FOR SCIENTISTS, IIT, CHICAGO, IL — AUG 2006-PRESENT

 Inspire data science, health physics, applied math, and other students to craft compelling narratives based on communication and design fundamentals.

VOLUNTEER TECHNICAL ADVISOR, ORDINARY PEOPLE INTL, NFP, CHICAGO, IL-2011-PRESENT

Developed print and online content to promote community development efforts.

Education

Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, IL - M.S. & Ph.D. in Technical Communication, 2013

References

Available upon request.

Skills

- Qualitative rapid
 & embedded research
- Remote & in-person research
- In-depth interviews
- Survey development, deployment, & monitoring
- Diary studies
- Competitive analysis
- Journey mapping
- Analysis & Reporting
- Insight development
- Discussion facilitation
- Client communications
- Familiar with mixed methods
- Multimedia storytelling
- Data visualization
- Web dev (front-end)
- Digital & print design
- Science communication

Tools

- Analytics
- Microsoft 365
- Adobe CC
- Mural
- dscout
- HTML & CSS
- · CMS systems
- Salesforce
- Qualtrics

Personal Skills

- Strong organization skills
- Ability to multi-task
- Attention to detail
- Interpersonal and collaborative
- Self-motivation
- Effective at learning new & emerging tools
- Remote & in-person work